<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Administrivia on PHYS52015 – Introduction to HPC</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/</link><description>Recent content in Administrivia on PHYS52015 – Introduction to HPC</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><atom:link href="https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Remote editing/development</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/remote/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/remote/</guid><description>Remote development and managing changes # Remote editing # Editing in a terminal is somewhat painful, and laboriously copying files back and forth between your local machine and Hamilton is error-prone.
A better approach is to use a combination of version control and remote editing. I provide brief instructions for VS Code which is a popular editor, and very brief instructions for Emacs.
VS Code # VS Code has an extension for remote editing which allows you to edit files on remote systems as if you&amp;rsquo;re running locally.</description></item><item><title>Hamilton access &amp; quickstart</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/hamilton-quickstart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/hamilton-quickstart/</guid><description>Accessing Durham Supercomputing facilities # Most of the exercises in this course will require that you use one of Durham&amp;rsquo;s supercomputing systems. This will either be Hamilton, or (for some Physics students) COSMA. If you&amp;rsquo;re signed up on the course, you should have been given access to Hamilton semi-automatically (I signed everyone up).
Access to Hamilton # For many of the exercises in the course, we will be using the Hamilton supercomputer.</description></item><item><title>Local setup</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/byod/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/byod/</guid><description>Running the exercises on your own hardware # Although you don&amp;rsquo;t need to, you might find it useful or convenient to run the exercises on your own computer. To do so, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to obtain appropriate compilers and MPI implementations.
For more general information on getting a development toolchain setup, the Faculty of Natural Sciences at Imperial College have prepared some useful guides
MacOS # Open source tools # I recommend homebrew for installation of packages on MacOS.</description></item><item><title>ssh configuration</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/configuration/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/configuration/</guid><description>ssh tips &amp;amp; tricks # Setting up simpler logins # It can be tedious to remember to type long login commands every time when logging in via ssh to hamilton. I therefore recommend that you set up an ssh config file.
Additionally, you might also want to set up ssh keys for passwordless login.
The ssh-config configuration file # Mac/Linux When you run ssh it reads a configuration file at $HOME/.</description></item><item><title>Unix resources</title><link>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/unix/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://teaching.wence.uk/phys52015/setup/unix/</guid><description>Using Unix-like systems for computational science # This course presupposes some level of familiarity with commandline interfaces. In case you need a quick refresher, I recommend the material produced by the Software Carpentry project.
They have a number of useful lessons and materials providing introductory training on how to do things like use the Unix shell, version control with git, and some introductory programming and plotting in Python. They are good place to start for a gentle introduction to these topics.</description></item></channel></rss>